Finding Aid for Letitia J. Byrd Papers, 1932-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Letitia J. Byrd Papers
1932-2009
Byrd, Letitia J.
05132 Aa 2
Letitia J. Byrd is an African-American local community leader and a counselor for Huron High School in the Ann Arbor Public School system. She is also very involved with other Ann Arbor community organizations. This collection includes photographs, professional correspondence, and documents recording her involvement with numerous local organizations and with the Ann Arbor School System.
1 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Letitia J. Byrd (donor no. 9505 ) and came to the library in June 2005.
The collection is open to research.
Letitia Byrd was born in Bluefield, W.Va. She received her Bachelor's of Science in Music Education and Business Administration from Bluefield State College, Bluefield, W.Va. and earned her Master's in Guidance and Counseling from Eastern Michigan University. In 1966, she married David R. Byrd, architect. The couple settled in Michigan where she became the first African American teacher at Forsyth Junior High in Ann Arbor. Later, she became a Huron High School Counselor. Outside of work, she was an active member of the Ann Arbor community. She was a member of the U-M Musical Society, a member and chapter president of The Links, Inc., the first president of the local chapter of the Delta Sigma Theta Sorority, a member of the National Council of Negro Women, a member of the Board of Directors for Dawn Farm, and many other local organizations in which she participated.
The Letitia J. Byrd papers include photographs, correspondence and documents regarding the life of Letitia Byrd, her career in the Ann Arbor Public School System, and her community activism.
Subjects:
Byrd, Letitia J.; African American women educators--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor Public Schools.; Social service--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women educators--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Ann Arbor Public Schools
  The Ann Arbor Public Schools series, 1970-1991 (0.40 linear feet) is arranged alphabetically by topic. The series includes records regarding her involvement with administrative committees and correspondence with colleagues and students.
  - African Connections, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor News-Minority Student Internship, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Black Student Union, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Black Youth in Ann Arbor Public Schools, 1983-1987 (Box 1)
  - Black Youth Task Force, 1982. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Ann Arbor News, 1976; 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Dr. Richard Benjamin (Superintendent), 1984-1989 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Miscellaneous, 1974-1991 (Box 1)
  - Documents, Miscellaneous (includes resume), 1970s (Box 1)
  - Four-Year High School Committee, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Michigan School Counselors Association, President, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Multicultural Steering Committee
    - General Activity, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. Day, 1984; 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Professional Staff Development, 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - Recommendation Letters, 1978; 1980 (Box 1)
  - Task Force Self-Worth Committee, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous Organizations
  The Miscellaneous Organizations series, 1975-2004 (0.50 linear feet) is arranged alphabetically by organization. The series includes records, such as correspondence and meeting minutes, regarding her activities with each organization.
  - African-American Cultural and Historical Museum, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Alliance for Achievement in Academics and in the Arts, Board of Directors (with photos), 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Symphony Orchestra, Vice President-Minority Affairs, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Community Development Block Grant, Executive Committee, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - David R. Byrd Center, 2007-2009 (Box 1)
  - Dawn Farm, Board of Trustees (with photos), 2003-2004 (Box 1)
  - Delta Sigma Theta Sorority, National Nominating Committee, 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - Huron Valley Child Guidance Clinic, Board of Directors, 1995-1997 (Box 1)
  - Leaders in Prevention, 1988 (Box 1)
  - The Links, Inc
    - Directories, 1986-1993 (Box 1)
    - General Activity, 1980-1993 (Box 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1988-1993 (Box 1)
    - Programs, 1989-1993 (Box 1)
  - National Council of Negro Women, Scholarship Award Committee, 1980-1982 (Box 1)
  - Peace Neighborhood Center, Jazz-Tap Summit Committee, 1998 (Box 1)
  - SOS Community Crisis, Board of Directors, 1991 (Box 1)
  - United Negro College Fund, Historical Committee, 1992 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan, School of Nursing, Minority Affairs Committee, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - University Musical Society, Board of Directors, 1999 (Box 1)
  - University Musical Society, Choral Member, 1975-1980 (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw Community College Foundation-Women's Council, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw Community College Community Recognition Committee, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw Family Services, Collaborative Council, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw Family Services, Training Committee, 1995-1997 (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw United Way, 1986 (Box 1)
- Personal
  The Personal series, 1950s-1995 (0.10 linear feet) consists of four folders. One folder contains photographs of her, of her family, and of acquaintances, all are undated. Another folder contains newspaper clippings that mention her or her family. The last two folders contains materials associated with her work during her enrollment in the University of Michigan's Gerontology Certificate program.
  - Miscellaneous certificates, recognitions and awards, 1932-1998 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Family Announcements, 1976-1995 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Gerontology Certificate Program, Internship Materials, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Gerontology Certificate Program, Papers, 1977-1978 (Box 1)